<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Temporis filia veritas A mery devise called the troublsome travell of tyme, and the daungerous delivery of her daughter trueth. Interlocutours, Bennion the button-maker: and Balthesar the barber.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838233</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838233</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Temporis filia veritas A mery devise called the troublsome travell of tyme, and the daungerous delivery of her daughter trueth. Interlocutours, Bennion the button-maker: and Balthesar the barber.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printed abroad--STC.</note>
                  <note>A plea for religious tolerance--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B⁵.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2600:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Temporis Filia Veritas.</hi> A mery deviſe called <hi>the</hi> Troublſome travell of Tyme, and the daungerous delivery of her Daughter Trueth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Equity is gone aſyde, and Righteouſnes ſtandeth farre of, the Trueth is fallen downe in the ſtreets, and the thing that is playne, may not be ſhewed: The Trueth is layde in priſon, and he that refrayneth himſelfe from evill, muſt bee ſpoyled. <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſa. 59. a.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore thus ſayth the Trueth, thoſe myne Enemyes (which would not that I ſhoud Raygne ouer them) bring them hither, and ſlay them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my face. <bibl>
                     <hi>Luc. 19. c.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Geve no ſentence before thou haſt heard the cauſe, but firſt let men tell out ther Tales. <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. 11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>If a man love me he will keepe my ſayings, (ſayth Chriſt) and my Father will love him, yea, we will come vnto him and dwell with him. <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioan. 14. b.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Interlocutours,</hi> BENNION the Button-maker: and BALTHESAR the Barber.</p>
            <p>Anno 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2600:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2600:2"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BENION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ell ouertaken (neighbour BALTHASAR) where haue you bin this longe tyme? for I haue not ſeene you in your ſhoppe theſe 3. or 4. dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BALTHASAR.</speaker>
               <p>I have bin waſhing, ſhauing, and triming; in the Countrye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Then I truſt you can tell vs of ſome good newes? for men ſay all newes are to be heard of at a Smyths Forge, a Barbers ſhopp, or at a mill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>Verely I can heare of little or no good newes in the Contry to be had, wherefore I pray you neighbour Benion, tell me in ſadnes, what doe you heare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Suerly (neighbour) I can tell you of very good newes, wherat (I truſt to God) we all ſhall reioyſe, &amp; this is the matter: I came no ſooner into the Citty, and had gotten a Chapman for my buttons, (but in comming by a Smiths For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge) I heard ſay: there was a worthy Parlament appoynted and a gratious day ſet, wherin (euery man, conſerning his religion) ſhould be permitted freely to ſpeake without any lett, or interruption: and alſo heard without any perceality, And then whoſoeuer hath the beſt on his ſyde, in the Trueth; it was concluded that his religion ſhould take place, he preferred of the <hi>Kinge:</hi> and the Trueth ſet vp aboue all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>But (tell me) is that poſſible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Yea truly, but what would you ſaye if I were there preſent, and hearde all the ſame parley, euen from the beginning to the end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>Suerly I would ſay then that this Realme ſhould be moſt happy of all nations vnder the Sonne, yea and moreouer that the Lord would bleſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper ſuch magiſtrates in all things that they tooke in hand: Now therefore I pray thee tell me more of this matter, but waſt thou in deed from the beginning to the end of this parley?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>I heard al that was there ſpoken and concluded amongſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>What were the company there aſſembled, canſt thou tell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Yea: For there was none that ſate in Iudgment, vnleſſe they were of great dignity, honour, or worſhip: Videlicet.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Kinge which executeth true judgment without percealety: and he ſate vppermoſt in his royall ſeate:</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Counſell (which are good aduouching alwayes therunto) &amp; they ſate next vnto him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Lords Spiritual (who are zelous for the trueths cauſe) and were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced next them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lords Temperall who are redy to defend the Trueth) and they were placed next them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly the comons; who are redy to liue therin: (euery one of theſe aforeſayd, ſo much as they may attayne grace therto of the Lord) and they ſate in the nethermoſt roome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:2600:3"/>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>This was doubtleſſe a ioyfull ſight To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beholde: the Lord bleſſe them all, and geue them of his grace to haue all men ſpeake whithout perſeality: to judge vprightly: and alſo to eſtabliſh thoſe things that may redounde to Gods glory <hi>Amen:</hi> but what ſpeaker was appoynted to the ſame parlament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Such a one as in lyke maner feared the Lord, and is deſyerous that all things mought be done for the beſt according to Gods will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>Then (firſt of all) I pray thee let me heare what the ſpeaker ſayd: and what matters were their cheifly handled by him conſerning the effect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall cauſes of theyr aſſembly for it ſhould ſeeme (by this thy ſaying that there were matters handled of great importance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben</speaker>
               <p>Theſe or the lyke ſo farre as my memory would ſerve me were the words of the ſpeaker.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">SPEAKER.</note>For as muche as I at this tyme (although vnmeet therunto) am appoynted to ſpeake before the Kings highnes, as alſo before you all Right, high Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſhipfull here aſſembled, in matters appertayning to a common welth, ſowell for ſoule as body. Therefore muſt I firſt of all in moſt humble wiſe craue perdon of his Majeſtie, and alſo of all you Honorable, and worſhipfull in this audience that if any thing chaunce (for the want of ſkill audacitie, or wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) to eſcape my mouth, it may be taken to the beſt according to my good meaning. Thus it is ò moſt renoumed Prince, and you Honorable Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall &amp; temperall, together whith you worſhipfull, and commons of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlament here aſſembled &amp; alſo be it knowne vnto you all: That the cheif and principall thing wherethrough all Nations, Kingdoms, Princes, People, and commonwelths are vphoulden, kept, and preſerved from harmes and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is <hi>God,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> therefore, ought (of all Nations, Kingdoms, and People) moſt cheifly and aboue all other things to be feared, loued, obeyed, honored &amp; ſerved. And ſeeing that your calling is cheifly to that end: alſo that all your cares and Induſtryes is now gratiouſly bent therunto, in ſomuch as this honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſembly is come together there about: I beſeech you therefore (in the name of the ſame liuing <hi>God</hi>) to heare me For aſ-much as it is not vnknowne vnto the Kings highnes, as alſo to the honorable, and worſhipfull here aſſembled, that although the ſcriptures haue bin (to the ſame effect aforſayd: moſt plentifully read vnto the People theſe many yeres according to the Kings appoyntment and good intention yet not-withſtandinge we ſee that the liues of the People (for the moſt part) are become worſe and worſe, (ſowell among the learned, as among the layhood) and the cauſe is for that the Preachers themſelues, doe not deſyer to become ſuch as they would frame theyr hearers to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And not that alone but alſo by thAt meanes) and for the want of obedience; there are ſpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng vp, ſondry ſect; and ſortes of religions here among vs at this daye ſo thatt euery one (being notwithſtanding contrary mynded one towards an other) will haue his owne for the beſt yea although they muſt all needs graunt, that there is but one onely trueth [it would be to long to reſyte how many haue bin deceiued and are yet, through ſuperſtition and Idolatry, likewiſe how many (in
<pb facs="tcp:2600:3"/> theſe) haue taken to their ſelues A freedom and liberty of lyfe in comitting wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes] out of their miſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rſtuing of holy ſcriptures. And more ouer how m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny haue bin expulced the vniuerſities for their diſſobedience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> forſaken heir be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice and exhibition gathered together their conventikles, Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ached falſe and ſedicious doctrine, ronne here and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey myght be hearde, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge the People againſt obedience, due to the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, manly,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> and po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke lawes and ordinances of theyr Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and gouernours: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g vp of tumults: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t murdering and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng one of an other is come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e daylie (in other lands) therabout: videlicet about religion &amp; the True<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, it woulde be, I ſay, too long to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vie for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eedy reformation wherof, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that the lyke inconuenience in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h God forbid) co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not to paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with in this Land, but rather may in tyme (through your good providen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and Noble wiſdoms in the Lord) before ſeene and peruented. May it therefore pleaſe the Kings Majeſtie, the Lords Spirituall and Temperall together with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and commons here aſſemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, to let proclamation go forth into all coaſts of the Land, and that it be permitted and graunted, of euery Religion one (at the leaſt) to come into the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lament houſe, there to ſpeake freely his mynd conſerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trueth, and the effect or ground of his religion. And when euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one hath ſayd his mynde, and your princely wiſdome aduiſedly and deeply) conſidered therof, as which of them all ſhall go neareſt the Trueth: So may you then doe your beſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord that the Trueth onely may take place for aſ-much as <hi>God</hi> (who alone is worthy of all honour) is a ſpirit, and wil none otherwiſe be honored ſaue in ſpirit and Trueth. And thus, to thend all enuy, contencion and diſobedience, mought once ſeace amongſt vs (that now boaſt ſo much of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity) and that all godly loue obedience, vnity, peace and concord, in the Trueth, myght come in place, whereby God myght rightly be honored, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> myght faythfully be beleeued, the King and you all that beare authority; dutifully obayed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the People that are vnder you become bleſſed: and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth alwayes floriſh to your euerlaſting fame:] I make an end. Referring all thing here ſpoken to the Lord, and your wiſdomes to conſider of, and ſo I committ you to God and to his good tuicion, who is well able to endow you with his heauenly wiſdom or holy ſpirit for to doe in all, his wil <hi>Amen.</hi> And ſo he ended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>This was no doubt a maruellous good waie for to bring all to one vniformity of Religion, as alſo for to fynde out the Trueth: [if ſo be the King &amp; majeſtrates, when they haue harde all ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcerne the Trueth and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from all others] which thing they may eaſily doe when as the Lord ſhall ſee it good, for as much as the Trueth is playne, and ſeeketh no corners, and they alſo Gods Miniſters appoynted to that end, but yet thou haſt not tolde me what was ſayd to this matter, nor what enſued therupon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſayd the King this mans conſell is very good: let therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation go forth and let them come before vs [to wit] of euery Religion one: and then ſhall euery one ſay his mynde freely conſerning his Religion, and
<pb facs="tcp:2600:4"/> conſerning the Trueth: And (for my part after I haue heard euery one ſpeak, and aduiſedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered therof according vnto the Trueth of the Scriptures, I wil by the grace of <hi>God</hi> giue true Iudgement without perceality becauſe that <hi>God</hi> (whoſe miniſter I am) mought rightly be honored in <hi>Spirit</hi> and in <hi>Trueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſpake the Counſell, all at once, and ſayd, God ſaue thee <hi>(ò Kinge)</hi> for euer: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e likewiſe are good advouching thereunto, and therefore wiſh (with all our haertes) that it mought euen-ſo come to paſſe.</p>
               <p>After that ſpake the Lords Spirituall and ſayd, <hi>God</hi> bleſſe the <hi>King</hi> in his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, for we alſo are zealous for the Trueths cauſe, and therefore woulde gladly that it vvere manifeſted.</p>
               <p>And then ſpake the Lords Temperall and ſayd, <hi>God</hi> preſerue the <hi>King,</hi> and graunt him good ſuckceſſe in all that he taketh in hand: for vve are redy, to the vttermoſt of our power, to defend the Trueth, vvere it once made knowen.</p>
               <p>Then laſt of all ſpake the commons and ſayd, <hi>God</hi> proſper the <hi>King</hi> in his good purpoſe, for vvee ſtand alſo ready to liue therin, mought vve once know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynlie vvhich vvere the Trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt</speaker>
               <p>The God of all Trueth bleſſe them vvith his euerlaſting bleſſing: make manifeſt his Trueth vnto them, and then geve them and vs all grace to liue in the ſame. But vvhat followed I pray you tel me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Vpon this the proclamation vvent forth into all quarters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon came into the Parlament houſe 4. men diuerſly <hi>Apareled:</hi> alſo of ſundry myndes or Religions, Videlict A <hi>Catholick</hi> [comonly called a <hi>Papist.</hi>] A <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> [c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monly called a <hi>Liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in.</hi>] A <hi>Puritan</hi> [comonly called a <hi>Rebell.</hi>] And a playne <hi>Plowm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> vvhoſe religion vvas vnknowen, [comonly called an <hi>Hereti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</hi>]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt</speaker>
               <p>Now of Fellowſhip let me heate more of this matter, for there is like alwaeys to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſue ſome good ſporte, vvhere ſo many Players doe reſorte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben</speaker>
               <p>After ſuch tyme as they all (kneeling vpon their knees) had craued perdon, and liſence euery man to ſpeak freely his mynde, vvithout any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, for the profe of his Religion, and the manifeſting of the Trueth, and that free liberty vvas graunted them. Then vvas it concluded alſo, that the Catholick ſhoulde ſpeake firſt, next after him the Proteſtant, 3. the Puritane, and laſt of all the playne Plowman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>Suerly this vvas excellent vvel, now then (as thou loueſt me) let me heare vvhat good ſtuffe the Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> coulde bring for his old ruſty Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben</speaker>
               <p>Then the Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> after his humble ſubmiſſion made to the K. and to the Honourable and vvorſhipfull there aſſembled) he ſayd.</p>
               <p>Moſt Noble Prince, &amp; you all moſt Honourable &amp; worſhipfull audience: In as much as you haue moſt graciouſly graunted me to ſpeake for my Religion and the Trueth, ſo I moſt humbly beſeech you all to heare me: Be it knowne vnto you all that the Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> generall Religion, had her firſt foundacion, as it is thought, neare vpon 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hundred yeares paſt, and hath remayned in force [and no other generall Religion, among the Chriſtians with in <hi>Europe,</hi> knowen or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented] vntill about 80. yeares paſt, that one <hi>Matin Luther</hi> (ſome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ymes a ffryer)
<pb facs="tcp:2600:4"/> tooke vpon him, vpon a diſpleaſure taken aganſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, to vvryte diſpitefully there agaynſt: and this our Religion vvas inſtituted acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rding to the holy ſcriptures by a generall councell of holy Fathers: For after ſuch tyme as they, out of a great zeale towards the Trueth beheeld the increaſe of all Iniquity amongſt the People, in ſomuch as <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st</hi> and his doctrine vvas almoſt forgotten: yea and more ouer fearing leaſt, in proceſſe of tyme, the Natiuety, Death, and Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> together vvith his doctrine, lyfe and miracles, as alſo the doctrine, lyfe and miracles of the Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangileſts, and holy fathers, ſhould likevviſe be altogether forgotten, eſpecially n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w in theſe laſt liſencious dayes, vvherin they vnderſtood, in the <hi>Spirite,</hi> that all iniquity vvould abound, lyke as it is come to paſſe at this day: Then they thought it good to call a generall Councell at the vvhich counſell they ordayned, not vvithout the holy Ghoſt, the feſtiuall dayes throughout the yere, like as they yet remayne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church at this day) ſome in commemoration of Chriſtes Natiuety, ſome of his circumſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: ſome of his Death: ſome of his Reſurrection, and ſome of his Aſſention into heauen, &amp;c. Likewiſe they ordayned other Feſtiuall dayes in commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deaths and martirdomes of holy ſaints, videlicet. Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts Martirs, and confeſſors, &amp;c. They haue alſo ordayned holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ceremonyes, together vvith an vniformity of God-ſervice, to be vſed in the Church onely to houlde in memory before the People (in their right ſignifications) thoſe holy things vvhich the goſpel of Ieſu Chriſt requireth in the Deede) of all men: and yet notwithſtanding vvere then (almoſt of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) forgotten: Moreouer they ordayned and eſtabliſhed, that the <hi>Goſpells</hi> and <hi>Epistles,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be (as a New Teſtament) coadioyned to the olde: and read dayly in the Churches for holy ſcripture, and ſo to be taken for euer: they alſo ordayned and built many Churches for holy vſe, Faſtings, prayers, Almeſdeeds, confeſſion of ſinnes, vvith contricion and ſatiſfaction to be made for the ſame, with many other good things more vvhich vvere too longe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte: And now (right noble and honourable audience) in what Feare, obedience, and reaſonablenes the People vvere houlden (euen vntill this our laſt Age) vnder Catholick Religion, and her ſacraments and cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyes, I need not much to ſpeake of, but vvill rather leaue it to the Iudgmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and conſideration of all thoſe that be vviſe and of auncient yeares among you, &amp; knew their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation: And therefore (to be ſhorte) I hold my Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Religion to be of moſt antiquety, ordayned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſent of the holy Ghoſt, and grounded vpon the Trueth And thus I conclude, who ſoe houldeth vpon the Catholiq Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (In his Right Inſtitucion he houldeth vpon the True Religion: And who ſoe houldeth vpon the Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Church houldeth vpon the true Churche: And thus he ended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely (neighbour Benion) if this vvere his talke, and if this be true vvhich he hath ſayd: then this is the Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Religion (as I thincke) layd on ſuch a ground or foundacion, bringing alſo with it ſuch antiquety; that I know not preſently to the contrary, but he is lyke to beare a ray the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:2600:5"/> game, yet vvould I gladly heare how the proteſtant could anſwere this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Then the Proteſtant (after humble ſubmiſſion &amp;c.) ſayd: O moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince together vvith all you Honourable and worſhipfull, let me freely ſpeake before you: It is not vnknowne vnto you all at this preſent that this Popiſh Religion [although I graunt ſhe mought happely haue had ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ground in her firſt Inſtitution] hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n (ſince that tyme) diuerſly &amp; ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, altred &amp; patched, in ſomuch as ſondry Popes haue added ſundry ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes, Videlicet. ſome holy water, ſome holy bread, ſome other haue ſet vp (as bookes fot the vnlearned to looke vpon certaine Images, &amp; ſome haue graunted that oblations ſhould be made vnto them, ſome other that ſight ſhould be ſet before them other ſome haue alowed (for the vnlearned) beades for to nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theyr prayers withall: And ſome haue likewiſe (for monyes cauſe) graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out perdon for ſinnes, ſome in one maner ſome in an other: yea and their ſervice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherin they ment to ſerve God, was in a language that the People vnderſtood not [what ſhould I ſpeaka of Maſſes, Trentalts, and Dirges to be ſung for the Dead Hallowing of Palmes, of Croſſes, Churches and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeards, likewiſe of Chriſtning and hallowing of Bells &amp;c.] And this ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion continued (like as he ſayd therin right well) till M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> that famous Clarke, vvho hath diſcloſed all their ſuperſtition, Idolatry, Coui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, and whordome &amp;c. vvhich tyme vve God be thancked) haue had for the moſt part this our proteſtant Religion, vvherin the Goſpell or Trueth is ſincearely Preached: all ſuperſtition, Idolatry and abhomination altogether put downe, and god ſervice in the mother tongue, ſo that now euery Carter &amp; Cobler can whiſtle and ſing pſalmes, and euery man can reaſon and talke of the ſcriptures in euery place freely where they come: yea moreouer euery Biſhop and Miniſter may haue his wife &amp;c. And now (right honorable Audience.) what fruites and freedom this our liberty of the goſpell hath brought vvith it, ſince we began to preach, I need not to reſyte: but vvill referre that and all that I haue ſayd, vnto your vviſdoms to conſider of: Thus I conclude [Right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vvorſhipfull] that my Religion (ſet out and allowed by the Kinge and his Counſell) hath his ground and foundacion from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and therefore of greater antiquitie then the Catholike Religion by an hundred yeares and more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is therefore the beſt, and the goſpell vvhich vve preach (ſay I:) that is the Trueth. And therewith he made an end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt</speaker>
               <p>Lord haue mercy on vs, vvhat ſhall vve ſay that are vnlearned, in this troubleſome tyme of ſo many Religions and Opinions? or vvhom ſhal vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue? For now (if this vvere his tale, and this be true vvhich he hath ſayd: doubtleſſe he hath ſo firmely and groundly ſayd his plat forme (that in myne opinion) no man liuing can remoue it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or goe beyond him. And therefore I ſee not to the contrary, but that he muſt needs goe away vvith the victory, otherwiſe I am much deceaued: yet I pray thee let me heare vvhat the other could ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:2600:5"/>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſtood vp the Puritan, and (after ſubmiſſion done) he ſayd, moſt high and renoumed Prince together with you all that be Honourable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, like as ye haue heard theſe 2. men tell their tales concerning the ground of their Religions, and the Trueth: euen ſo I beſeech you heare me: It is vvell knowen vnto you all that I haue bin, euen for the Lord my God his cauſe, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous this 30 yeares and more, in ſo much as I haue bin expulced the Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes: depriued of my liuings: runne here and there, euen for my Conſcience cauſe, &amp;c and therefore haue matter ſo well againſt thee O <hi>King</hi> and thy Lawes, as alſo againſt them both and their Religions that haue here ſpoken: As f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r thee thou ſetteſt vp ſuperſtitious lawes vvhich are not correſpondent to Gods lawes, and therefore I will not obey them: And now to anſwere the Catholike and his <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Religion; I need not, for aſmuch as the Proteſtant hath ſufficiently anſwered him. But as conſerning the Proteſtant and his Religion (vvhich he ſo extolleth aboue all other) I am right vvel able to reproue him, almoſt in an 100. places vvhich he hath altogether taken out of the Romiſh ſincke, or ſtincking Popiſh puddle: like as you may eaſily ſmell from wence they came; if you do but a little holde vp your heads and beholde the ſituation of your Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, how they yet ſtand Eaſt and Weſt your ſteeples alſo full of Bells your Quiers and Alters, together vvith Coaps, veſtments and cornerd caps: Tippets, Rotchets, Sirpluſſes, proceſſions ſingings, organs &amp;c. [what ſhould I ſpeake of their ſuperſtitious names, <hi>Videlicet.</hi> my Lord of Canterburyes grace, my Lord Yorcks grace my Lord Biſhop, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Deane, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Subdeane, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Archdeacon, Mr. Commoſary: D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ſuch-a-on: M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Soueraigne, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Parſon, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Vicker, &amp;c. and (to be ſhorte) vvat ſoeuer the proteſtant vſeth (ſo vvel in his ſeruice, as in his miniſtration of Sacraments, and Ceremonyes) they are all counterfeyted out of Papiſtry: and are therefore no better to be termed then rotten Raggs of the Romiſh Church. For that cauſe (right Honourable audience) I beſeech you in the bowels of Ieſu Chriſt, that you vvoulde once ouerthrowe and cleane roote out for euer all ſuch Antichriſtan memorials aforeſayd of that Babiloniſh hoore, ſo that nothing remayne vpon the Earth in any remembrance of her: And then may you reforme Religion (as we ſhall Inſtruct you) after the maner of the beſt reformed Churches in all <hi>Europe.</hi> And vntill that tyme we wil ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey you nor your lawes, and Inſtitutions: [for in ſuch caſe ſay we; it is better to obey God then men.] And thus I conclude Right Noble and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: foraſmuch as our zeyle ſtandeth more towards God and his lawes then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lawes and ordinances of men; Therefore we (who are aboue, in our miniſtration, men or Angels doe holde our Religion to be the beſt, becauſe we ſeeke the reformation of the Church in all things that are amiſſe: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer we haue our foundation from <hi>Ezechia, Ioſia, Iudas Machabeus,</hi> &amp;c. and for that cauſe of greater antiquitie then them both And our miniſtration (which we vſe and teach among our Colleges in our exerciſes, and nightly conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikles) is the Trueth. And here I end: comitting all things herein touched, to your vviſdoms to conſider of. And ſo departed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:2600:6"/>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>O Lord! what ſhall I ſaye? or vpon what Religion ſhall I now ſtaye me, wherby I mought now find out the Trueth? then hath he ſo vnfolded it in ſuch ſorte, alſo layde his ground ſo ſure that all men vvhich heareth him (as I conjecture) muſt needs thinke that he (vvhich is ſo zealous for Gods cauſe: feareth not to reproue the King to his face: ſeeketh the reformation of the Church: and alſo bringeth vvith him the greateſt antiquitie) is like to preuayle, and alſo winne the beſt game. Yet vvould I fayne heare what the 4<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. could ſaye to all theſe profound and groundly reaſons. but alas, what ſhould a playne Plowman ſaye among ſuch high learned Prelats? Notwithſtanding of fellowſhip let me heare what the fooliſh fellowe could ſay, or what anſwer he could make that I might laugh a little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Laſt of all ſtood vp this playne Plowman [whoſe Religion was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen: although he had bin ſo long tyme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by all theſe 3 aforſayd ſuſpected &amp; bruted for an Hereti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>] And (falling downe vpon his knees) he ſayd: O moſt puiſſant Prince together vvith all your Honorable and vvorſhipfull in this preſent Parlament aſſembled. Are you deſyerous (in this contentious and troubleſome tyme, wherin all Iniquity doth abounde and wherin alſo ſo many Religions, ſects, and opinions, are out of fleſh and bloud, entred or taken on among the Children of men) to vnderſtand the beſt Religion, as alſo the Trueth, and what thing the Trueth is, to thend that God mought be honoured therin? Then I beſeech you of your clemencie heare me ſpeake.</p>
               <p>You haue heard of theſe 3. (one being contrary to an other:) ſpeake the very beſt that in them was for the aduouching of their Religion and the Trueth: And now as touching the firſt [namely the Catholike] he hath out of a good zeale brought in, ſo nere as he could conjecture, the firſt ground of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Religion, and the long continuance thereof: declaring alſo that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>14</hi> a. b c <hi>1.</hi> Ioan. <hi>3.4.</hi> a.b.c.</note> ſignes, ceremonyes, and ſeruices of the ſame Church, were ordeyned onely to keepe in memory things paſſed &amp;c. [euen like as the ſeruices and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ceremoniall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old lawe were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning ordeyned to keepe in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie things that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were to come &amp;c. Notwithſtanding the good life where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon all ſacraments, ſignes, ceremonies, or ſhadowes figuratiue in the Catholik church did point vpon, and vvhich alſo the holy ſcripture doe require, and whereout the dutifull obedience towards God and Gouernours doth proceed, (was of this Catholicke now in theſe laſt dayes) altogether forſaken, rejected and forgotten: (euen like as it vvent alſo in times before with the diſobedient and vnbeleeuing jewes,) &amp; ſo hath he forſaken the Trueth, vvhereupon he ſayth his Religion was grounded: And therefore the Lorde hath now no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this Apoſtated Catholik nor yet in his abſurd Religion, vvherevpon it is now come to paſſe that the 2. (namely this Proteſtant) beholding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-maner abuſes and diſorderlyneſſe of life which hath bin now in theſe latter dayes, found in this Cotholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> and his Religion: and for the vvhich
<pb facs="tcp:2600:6"/> no doubt he hath receiued greate chaſtiſment of the Lord, and his Miniſters hath declared forth (to his great reproach) many of the ſame abuſes before you all very rightly as they vvere, and moreouer (out of a great zeale) hath commended his owne Religion for the beſt which thou (O king) haſt now appointed and ſet vp among vs: <hi>Videlicet,</hi> the declaring forth of the goſpell and holy ſcriptures among vs. The ſeruice vſed and read in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother tongue, to thend all mought heare and vnderſtand what is ſayd, and then followe the ſame vvhich is good: as likewiſe the ſacraments &amp; ceremonies miniſtred in the ſame tongue, to thend all ſubjects mought be holden vnder godly and manly obedience, and hue according to the ſcriptures in one vniformity of Religion according to the kings good meaning therein.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1. <hi>and.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Math.</hi> 25. <hi>d.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> All theſe [ſay I] were it accompliſhed in the deed and in the Trueth is a very good Religion, alſo vvere very vvell ſayde of him as out of a ſinguler good zeale.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the vvhile this Proteſtant (vvhich can readily reproue an other by the ſcripture) vvalketh forth ſtill in all malitiouſnes of life (although he boaſte neuer ſo much of Light, Life, Liberty,<note place="margin">Pſa. <hi>15.</hi> Ioan. <hi>12.</hi> g. Rom. <hi>8.</hi> b. Math. <hi>7.</hi> d. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.</hi> b. Collo. <hi>3.</hi> a. <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi> a.</note> &amp; Freedome by Chriſte) he remayneth notwithſtanding in darkenes and is the ſeruant of ſinne, or bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue of Sathan: (vvhat ſhould I ſay of the couitouſnes, that vvorſhipping of Images, Enuie, Pride, Extortion, Symony, Vſery, Whoredome together vvith all maner of Iniquity that now doth abound in this Proteſtant, ſo vvell among the Clergie as the Layetie.</p>
               <p>Thus may vve ſee that he likevviſe in rejecting the good life,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>14</hi> a. <hi>12.</hi> g. Gal. <hi>2.</hi> d. Math. <hi>5. 2.</hi> Ioan. <hi>4.</hi> b.</note> (vvhich all the holy ſcriptures, do requier and witnes: and were vpon alſo all the holy ſcriptures as alſo al ſacraments, ceremonies, figures or ſhadowes that good are) do ſignifie, figure forth, &amp; point vpon, hath rejected the Trueth. And novv beholde I pray you what fruits haue inſued ſince this liberty of life hath bin taken on? For the longer this Proteſtant hath preached vnto the people, the worſe the liues of the ſame people are become:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8 <hi>a</hi> 13 <hi>a</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eſd.</hi> 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 3.4.</note> experience hath taught vs: and no maruell, for he [in forſaking the good life] hath there withal forſaken the Trueth: and for that cauſe onelie, the Lorde hath no pleaſure in this licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Proteſtant, nor yet in his abſurd Religion.</p>
               <p>And as touching the 3. [namely the Puritan] for as much as he vvill not liue as a ſubject vnder all good lawes and ordinances of Kings &amp; Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3 <hi>a.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>a. b.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. <hi>a.</hi> 4. <hi>b. Ioan.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore hath (out of enuious perſumption, and rebellious heart) forſaken the obedience and godlie lyfe, due to <hi>God,</hi> and gouernors [notwithſtanding it is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired of vs all in holy ſcripture] ſo hath he in lyke maner there vvith all forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Trueth [it vvere too muche to name how many honeſt hearted and true faythfull ſubjects, to their Prince haue bin, by this Puritan, belyed ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered, perſecuted, and impriſoned, for that they held them to obedience and the good lyfe, like as they were taught:<note place="margin">Mala <hi>3.4.</hi> Pſa. <hi>50.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ioan. <hi>13.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and would neuer conſent to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellyous doctrine, nor come to his nightly conuentikles:] and therefore (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:2600:7"/> he, out of his great zeale, ſought the reformation of the Church, and yet he himſelf not reformed vnto obedience and godlines of lyfe) God hath no more pleaſure in this diſobedient Puritan nor yet in his abſurd Religion.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Eſd.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi>
                  </note> Thus you may ſee Right Noble,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>3.</hi> d. Ioan. <hi>8.</hi> d. Mar. <hi>8.</hi> d. Ioan. <hi>15.</hi> a. Ioan. <hi>14.</hi> a. Ioan. <hi>8.</hi> d. Luc. <hi>8.</hi> b. Mar. <hi>4.</hi> b. Matth. <hi>13.</hi> b. Eſa <hi>6.</hi> c. Ioan. <hi>12.</hi> f. g.</note> Honourable and vvorſhipfull, how euery one, in his vvay, ſeeketh religiouſly after the Trueth, if he myght any way fynde it. And againe you may ſee alſo that the Trueth is neuertheleſſe, hid from them all. And why? for (if we conſider of the Scriptures) vnto all thoſe that walke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the true lyfe, and godly obedience (which is required in gods holy vvord) all things chaunce in ſimilitudes, parables, and cloſed bookes: becauſe that men ſhould not ſee with their earthly eyes or myndes, nor heare with their earthly eares or thoughts, nor yet comprehende in theyr darke ſtony harts, the ſecrete works of the Holy Spirit of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>14.</hi> b.c. <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.</hi> Rom. <hi>13.</hi> a. <hi>2.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> a</note>For that cauſe all People that are zelous for Religion, &amp; for the Trueths ſake, [be they what they be, or dwell they where they ſhall: ſo they loue God, and deſyer to liue vnder obedience to the King and his good lawes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or, at the leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, liueth quietly and harmeleſly among the People, bearing a true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart to the Prince of the Land] are to be borne withall in their ignorant zeale for Conſcience ſake, in aſmuch as all good gifts proceed from God, yea and moreouer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 13.</note> for that the tyme of harueſt is at hand, in the vvhich the Lord vvill ſend out his Angels, to gather together the good wheat into his barnes &amp; to burne the weeds with vnquenchable fyer.<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>1.</hi> a. b. <hi>14.</hi> a. Ioan. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> e. f. Ioan. <hi>17. 2.</hi> Ioan. <hi>4.</hi> b.</note> For doubtles the Trueth it ſelf (wherabout men ſo ſtriue) is an other maner of thing then fleſh and bloud was euer able to fynd out, for it is the louely lyfe, or being of God, or of his holy word, vvhich lyfe is the thing (as I ſayd before) that all ſacrifices, ſignes, or ſhadowes in the whole lawe, as alſo the Sacraments and ceremonyes of the new Teſtament ordained in the Chriſtian Catholicke Church together with all that the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>3.</hi> a b. c. d. &amp;c. Ioan. <hi>16.</hi> d. e. f <hi>17.</hi> c. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</hi> c. Gen. <hi>2.</hi> b. 3. a. Prov. <hi>3.</hi> c. Apo. <hi>2.</hi> b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. <hi>15.</hi> c. Gen. <hi>3. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi> d. <hi>3.</hi> a. b. c. Deut. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> a. b <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>3.</hi> a. <hi>1.</hi> Pet <hi>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> Matth. <hi>7.</hi> b. Ioan. <hi>13.</hi> d. <hi>14 15.</hi> Gal. <hi>2.</hi> d. e. Ioan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Gen. <hi>2</hi> b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. a. d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> a. b c.</note> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oynt vpon: ſignify and requier at all our Hands, I ſay, once agayne, the louely lyfe of God, or of his holy worde is the very Trueth [namely <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi>] It is alſo the Tree of lyfe that was pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the beginning in the midſt of the Paradiſe, or Luſt-garden of the Lord [which tree of lyfe, euen like as the firſt, through the diſobedience in the knowledge, hath loſt the ſame: euen ſo the ſecond man through the obedience in the lyfe, winneth the ſame agayne] it is very true: And therefore to liue in Obedience to God and his holy vvord, alſo in obedience to the King, and his good lawes and ordinances, and to loue myne neighbour as myne owne ſelfe, alſo to deale louingly &amp; vprightly vvith all men like as I vvould be dealt with all. is the effect of my religion, grounded vpon the Trueth, vvhich obedience had his originall from <hi>Adam, Abell, Seth, Noah, Abraham,</hi> &amp;c and is alſo confirmed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, &amp;c. and therefore ſhal continue for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>13</hi> c. <hi>14</hi> a <hi>15.</hi> a. b. c <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>13. 2.</hi> Ioan. <hi>3.</hi> a.b. c. <hi>4,</hi> a.b.</note>Thus I conclude that my Religion, in the good lyfe, goeth beyond them all, ſo farre as the Heauens from the Earth, or the Light from Darknes, alſo that all maner of Religious people (boaſt they neuer ſomuch of their Religions, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, Seruices, Sacraments Seremonyes, Freedomes by Chriſt, or elſwhat)
<pb facs="tcp:2600:7"/> that are found vvithout this obedience to <hi>God</hi> and Gouernours,<note place="margin">Ioan <hi>8.</hi> a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>8</hi> d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oan. <hi>14</hi> a b. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> Eph <hi>4</hi> a.b. c. <hi>6.</hi> b c. Ioan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Colo. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> b.</note> &amp; vvithout this goodlyfe aforeſayd (or at the leaſt haue not any earneſt inclination thereto, ſomuch as they may in the Lord) the Religion, their God ſeruice, and all els that they boaſt vpon, is nothing worth in the Lords ſight: and the cauſe is they haue forſaken the Trueth, vvhich is the flower and beauty of all good Religions ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and is all in all.</p>
               <p>Now haue I ſhewed you [Right High and Honorable:] the inconfutable ground of my Religion [which <hi>God</hi> of his gracious goodnes hath made knowen vnto me,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>Ioan</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>a. b.</hi>
                  </note> and for the vvhich I haue bin long ſuſpected] together vvith the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Trueth, vvherout all right obedience vnto <hi>God</hi> and Gouernours proſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and vvherout alſo the right repentance appeareth,<note place="margin">Gal <hi>2.</hi> d. <hi>3.</hi> a. b d Ioan. <hi>14</hi> a b. Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Colo <hi>1</hi> c. Ioan. <hi>8.</hi> d. <hi>15.</hi> a.</note> and the true and liuing fayth is alwayes working by loue, ſo well towards God and Chriſt, alſo towards my neighbour: and vvherunto I meane [by the grace of God] to indevour my ſelf night and day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by prayer and ſupplication, to thend I mought once attayne to the ſame Trueth, vvithout the vvhich there is, for me, no Salvation.</p>
               <p>Therefore conſider hereof aduiſedly, I moſt humbly beſeech you) ſo many as haue rejected obedience, they haue rejected the true Religion:<note place="margin">Eph <hi>4.</hi> d. Ioan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. c Ioan. <hi>14</hi> a.b. Hab. <hi>1.</hi> a. Gal. <hi>2.</hi> d.</note> And ſo many as haue rejected the holy and godly lyfe, haue rejected &amp; forſaken the Trueth, [namely <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>] Therefore am I boulde to ſay (as vnder correction and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) that this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Religion, and this Trueth, vvhereof I haue ſpoken, being once faſt grounded in our myndes and ſpirits, is the principall good wherein the Lord hath ſet his whole delight, and vvherout he vvil onely be honored &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: Alſo vverunto all Chriſtian and Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Religions, Kings, Princes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates &amp; people ought of right, for evermore to geue place, as one flocke vnder one ſhepheard: For it is an Euerlaſting lyfe, in the which, and through which, vve (being vnited ſoule and ſpirit vvith God the Father ſhall riſe againe (in this ſame fleſh,) and liue vvith <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Sauiour, in ioyes everlaſtingly: It is very True.</p>
               <p>And now as I haue here acknowledged (right High and Honorable, &amp;c be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you all) one onely true Chriſtian Catholik Religion: ſo let no man from hence forth charge me to be of no Religion, neither yet to be of all Religions, but rather ſuch a one as would good vnto all, [to vvit] that all religions, in moſt louing vviſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mought be gathered together (now in theſe laſt dayes) according to the promiſſes, through the goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> vnto this onely true Religion aforeſayd, of faythfull obedience to <hi>God</hi> &amp; Gouernours, and Trueth towards all men. For then vvhoſoeuer is a right Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Proteſtant or Puritan, and liueth in the ſayd obedience and Trueth, I can in no vviſe diſalowe of him, in ſomuch as I my ſelf indevour me dayly (by the grace of God) to accompliſh or attayne vnto, vvith them, that moſt holy religion of obedience and Trueth: becauſe there mought bee no more, in thend, ſaue one God, one Chriſt and ſauiour, one Holy Ghoſt, one Fayth, one Baptiſme, one obedience, one Trueth, one Flocke, one ſhepheard, euen ſuch is my mynd, &amp; ſo would I bee conceived of, and no other vviſe,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2600:8"/>
               <p>Great is the King, great and mighty is his power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea greate is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dge that the ſonnes of men haue found out vpon the Earth. Alſo great and many maner are the Religions, ſervices, and ceremonyes which men haue deuiſed to ſerue the Lord w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll: yet notwithſtanding much greater is obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the Trueth [That louely lyfe of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od,</hi> or of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s holy vvord] for it is, as I ſayd before <hi>Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus,</hi> the vvay, wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, the Trueth, vvherin all men ought to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: And the lyfe, wherin all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to liue. Therefore great is <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e lun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the Trueth, and of worthynes part goeth beyond them all. And ſo after reverence done he ended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
               <p>O moſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcyfull God: what ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> become of all ſuch Igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ules as I am? which are redy to runne, now af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er this Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion, then after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? [alas neighbour alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>] i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eemeth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by theſe his ſpeeches (which doubtles are very true,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>8</hi> d Mar. <hi>1.</hi> b. <hi>6.</hi> b. Ioan. <hi>15.</hi> a.b.</note> that all People on Earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich haue choſen to them ſelves a Religion wherin they ſuppoſed to haue obtayned their freedome, Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſalvation by <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and yet neuer attayned to true repentance, mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h leſſe to Obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, in the godly lyfe (vvhich he call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the Trueth, or Chriſt himſelf) are cleane ſet beſyde the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dle. For I now perceaue right well, the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edience in the good lyfe is a moſt precious treaſure proſeeding from God, and vvherewith God, the King, and a mans neighbour is ſerued Moreouer, by the lyfe men may knowe the workes of God from the workes of men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes: As for example, let vs looke vpon all the Creatures that the Lord hath made (yea wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tſoeuer thing the eye of man can beholde) and ſee, it hath or it hath had, a kynde of lyfe in it. Likewiſe, let vs looke vpon all the workes of man ſeeme they neuer ſo bewtifully and loe they haue no lyfe in them: So that although one man may faſhion an other man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. <hi>13.</hi> Ioan. <hi>14</hi> a.b. Ioan. <hi>3.</hi> a. Gala. <hi>6.</hi> c.</note> through ſmoth words &amp; deepe knowledges to an outward ſhew of holines yet is he no better [before ſuch tyme as <hi>God</hi> worketh, through his grace, and the miniſtration of his holy word, the new birth, or true godly lyfe in the man] then a dead Image, or paynted Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher which the man had made vvith his owne hands, And now therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it cometh red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly to my remembrance how it ſtandeth written in the Scriptures to the ſame effect:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Gala</hi> 4. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 3 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. c.</note> Videlicet, <hi>Except Christ be in you [ſayth Paul to the Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations] you are cast awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> alſo if a man haue not the ſpirit of God, the ſame is none of his, &amp; moreouer I trauell in birth till Chriſt be faſhioned in you agayne a newe (with a number of ſuch like ſavings in ſcriptuer more vvhich vvere too long to reſite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13. 1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.</hi> Ioan. <hi>14.15.</hi> a. b. c. d.</note> So that now I perceaue his mynd right well whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h is this, he that obayeth the vvord, obayeth the King, and leadeth a godly lyfe, and he that leadeth a godly lyfe hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling in him. And herefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayth: without me ye can doe nothing,<note place="margin">Ioan <hi>8</hi> d. Gal. <hi>2.</hi> d. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.</hi> a. Eph. <hi>5.</hi> a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ioan <hi>4.</hi> b. c.</note> for I am the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. the Trueth, and the Lyfe: So then when any good worke is wrought, it is <hi>Chriſt</hi> onely that doth the good-work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are acceptable vvith God, and not the man: and therefore vvhere he ſo extolleth the Trueth or good lyfe aboue all he meaneth <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> vvhich ought to dwell in the man, vvhoſe ſpirit, at that tyme, vvill lead the man into all
<pb facs="tcp:2600:8"/> right obedience and Trueth, vvhich lyfe doubtleſſe I ſee now, being wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of, is the principall good, vvherunto all People (vvith their high know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Religions, Services, Sacraments, and Ceremonyes, ought for evermore, to geve place. And now therefore (in myne opinion) if any man ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth reſiſt or deny thiſ ſame playne Plo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mans Religion, or he T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueth afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, vvhich is now ſo manyfeſtly expreſſed &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the holy ſcriptures, (his conſcience b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>g him record that it is euen ſo then doubtleſſe he is ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnorant and ſuperſticious Papiſt, vvho (being digreſſed from the right ground of the Cath li<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Religion) eſteemeth more of the Sacraments, Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes Ceremonyes or ſhadows, then of the very thing vvhich hey ſignify, or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue hidden in them: Or els he is a liſencious Proteſtant (vho contrary to the vvord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God, as alſo contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to the good meaning of the King) abuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h that goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on vvhich his Majeſte hath appoynted to be frequented amongſt vs and liueth af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er his owne filthy luſts and deſyers, Eyther alſo he is a diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and rebellious <hi>Puritan,</hi> vvho being altogether inclyned to Envy, Pryde, and preſumption ſhameth not to reſiſt the good lawes of the King,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> and in ſteed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>f to ſet vp his owne Imaginations, meaning thereby to alluer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the People from their dutifull obedience to God and gouernours, whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſcience ſhall in the end teſtify agaynſt him (and if he repent not in tyme) to his owne condemnation. But now I would gladly knowe, how all things were taken in the end: And whoſe Religion was beſt accepted of the King, and the reſt there aſſembled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>After great aduiſe and deliberation taken among them all: The King ſayd, this Plowman hath, laſt of all, manifeſted vnto vs (in playne ſpeech) the right Rel gion and the very Trueth (which may not in any wiſe be denyed) Therefore great is Obedience &amp; great is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trueth:<note place="margin">Mar. <hi>12.</hi> a.</note> I ſee well now that it was not for naught that it ſtandeth written: I am the God of <hi>braham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Iaco.</hi> 2. <hi>c. d.</hi>
                  </note> the God of <hi>Iſack</hi> &amp; the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> [a God of the Liuing but not of the Dead] Let Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamation the efore goe forth into all parts of the Land: and let it alſo be made knowen from vs the King (to all mens preſervation) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t he which wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtyan, and would be ſaved by <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> muſt (after true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) ſhewforth the fruits of fayth, in his obedience and Chriſtian lyfe.</p>
               <p>Then laſt of all ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke the Counſell, the Lords Spiritual and Temperall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Commons (all at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce) and ſayd l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de honour and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuing be to that God for euer more which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h gev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n us ſuch a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe King to raigne ouer vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat can ſo righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly diſcerne the beſt Religion and the Trueth from all others and thereupon g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n true Iudgement wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hout parceal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, And now if vve ſhould not henceforth auouch publiſh for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, mayntayne, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as alſo liue according to the ſame (ſo farre-forth as God ſhall geue vs gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e then vvere vve very much to blame becauſe that vve ſee that Obedience is the thing that the Lord hath commaunded all men to liue in: yea and more, it
<pb facs="tcp:2600:9"/> is whereby we his Miniſters Rule and gouerne vnder him in peace &amp; quietnes: Alſo that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> (once dwelling in vs) is the Trueth or good lyfe it ſelf, ſo faſt coupled vnto Fayth, as is the <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> vnto brightnes, or fyer vnto heat: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bringeth with it everlaſting lyfe and felicity. And ſo the Parlament brake vp, and I came away.</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KING Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <hi>Behold euen through ſuch a great Trouble and trauell aforeſayd, will gentle Ladye</hi> Tyme, <hi>bring forth her most bewtifull Daughter</hi> Trueth: <hi>now in theſe last daungerous dayes, to the glory of</hi> God, <hi>the preſeruation of Princes, and to an euerlaſting peace among all People.</hi>
            </closer>
            <closer>Amen. Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2600:9"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>After ſuch tyme as I had conſidered the many-maner of Religions, Sects, and Opinions, (gentle Reader) that are now riſen vp out of mens high knowledge and goodthinking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whereout (for the moſt parte) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeedeth alſo all contention, Envy, Diſobedience, Rebellion, Lying, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting, Slaundering, Impriſoning, Killing, &amp; Murdering, &amp;c, together with al liberty of life in committing wickednes, which is now frequented (without feare or ſhame) among the children of men. I tooke this deuiſe in hand for ſix ſpeciall cauſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt was for that the Magiſtrats (who are Gods miniſters on earth) mought the better remember their office and calling, and how that they are appointed of the Lord to ſuppreſſe euill, Diſobedience, Falſhood, and wickednes: and to maintayne Gods obedience, Trueth, or godlynes of lyfe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was for that all ſimple and ignorant people, mought ſee how eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men may be ſeduced [now in theſe dangerous dayes] through faire ſpeeches, and outward ſhewes of holines: yet neuertheleſſe I am not againſt the right Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, the true Proteſtant, or the perfect Praeciſian, ſo long as they holde them to Obedience in the holy life aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>The third was for that my hope ſtandeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, there are many good willing hearts to the righteouſnes yet remayning vpon the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.</hi> c.d. <hi>6.</hi> c. Rom. <hi>8.</hi> a. c.</note> who once knowing the Trueth, (and what euerlaſting felicitie it bringeth with it) will not (by any ſiniſter meanes of the diſobedient and rebellious route) be drawne away therefrom (whether it be then by theyr ſmothe ſpeeches, cruell threats, feare of Perſecution, Blaſphemyes, Tyranous handling, Impryſonments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>10.</hi> a. b. c. <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Vnjuſtice, or moſt cruell death that they can deuiſe (but will rather indevour them ſtill to liue vnder Obedience to God and gouernours &amp; ſo exerciſe them dayly in the godly life (that right Religion, faſt grounded on the vnconfutable Trueth) wherein the Lord had alwayes, ſtill hath, and for euermore ſhall haue his pleaſure and delight.</p>
            <p>The fourth cauſe was this,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> for that all men [if it were poſſible] mought ſee or vnderſtande that the good life is not ſo ſlight a thing as many men make accompte of. For the Lorde looketh not ſo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h vpon the outward oblations, Sacrifices, Seruices, or Ceremonyes, which the man offereth or vſeth for to ſerue him withall, as he doeth vpon the ſingle heart of the man,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>51.</hi> d. Ioh. <hi>4.</hi> c. Mar. <hi>12.</hi> c.</note> in his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and good lyfe [for the Lorde will be honoured onely (of his) in ſpirit and Trueth] therefore the Oblations, Seruices and Ceremonies, are reſpected of the Lorde for the good hearts cauſe and nor the euill hearted reſpected for the Oblations, Seruices, or ceremonies cauſe: Example by Cain and Abell,<note place="margin">Gen <hi>4.</hi> a.</note> they both offered ſacrifice to the Lord: The one (for the bloudynes of his heart) his
<pb facs="tcp:2600:10"/> Oblation was refuſed. And the other (for the ſinglenes of his heart) his Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was accepted. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The fift cauſe was for to anſwere and ſatiſfie all ſuch as praeſently ſtand (at the gaze as it were afarre-of) wayghting what will come of this my Religion, or els doubting of the goodnes and contynuance thereof. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi>
               </note>And the ſixt or laſt cauſe is this, for that I (who haue bin theſe many yeres moſt Injuriouſly ſlaundered and defamed: moſt cruelly perſecuted, and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, as alſo moſt diſpitefully ſpoyled and Impoueriſhed to my vtter diſcredit and vndoing: Like as ſome that be honourable (if they remember it) can part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell) am ſtill ready (during lyfe) to anſwere boldly for my felfe: beleefe, and Religion in the Trueth: And therefore (for the clearing of my ſelfe) and for the recouering of my good name [which I eſteeme aboue golde and ſyluer] I am bolde to dedicate this my deuiſe to her Majeſty, and to make knowne (there through) my Religion openly: And moreouer I meane hereafter [by Gods grace] and vnder correction and ſubmiſſion of my Prince, to perſwade all my friends, and acquaintance, whether they be then <hi>Catholi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>s, Proteſtants, Puritans,</hi> or what other Religions ſoeuer [ſo much as I may in the Lorde] to inclyne theyr hearts wholely to lyue vnder ſuch obedience and godlynes of lyfe, as is aforeſayde: Alſo to pray for the <hi>Queenes Majeſty</hi> and al the honourable of his priuie Counſell, for that they mought ſo maintayne the goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whereby the <hi>Trueth</hi> mought get the victorie in all our hearts: To the end all mought become one in <hi>Christ,</hi> And <hi>Christ</hi> one in all. AMEN.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2600:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
